I clearly told you to go.
我說得很清楚要妳離開
If you don't go now…
若妳現在不走
I'll never let go of your hand.
我就永遠不會放開妳的手
Did you get some sleep?
你有闔過眼嗎？
Why didn't you leave?
妳為什麼不先走？
I didn't want you to be alone when you woke up.
我不希望你醒來時孤伶伶的
I should get going.
我該走了
Okay.
好
Sleep more. I'll take the first bus.
再多睡一點，我會搭第一班巴士
Thank you.
謝謝
You stayed with me.
因為妳陪在我身邊
Thanks for that.
謝謝妳這樣做
As long as you're not mean to me,
只要你對我好一點
I can stay with you whenever you need me.
你需要我時，我都在你身邊
People use about ten facial muscles when they smile.
人笑的時候，臉部有十條肌肉都在動
But when they frown, they use almost all their facial muscles.
但是當人皺眉頭 就會用上幾乎所有的臉部肌肉
Instead of frowning with effort,
與其花力氣皺眉頭
I recommend that you fill your day with bright smiles.
我建議大家不如用微笑面對每一天
Sue's Morning Journey begins now.
《秀秀的晨間報報》現在開始
THE STORY OF THE AFTERLIFE
（《廣川的故事》）
IM CHEOL-U
（林吉羽）
"My poor children. Sorrow is your strength.
“我可憐的孩子，悲痛賦予你力量
Pain, resentment and remorse
痛苦、怨恨和悔恨
are your strengths.
都賦予你力量
With those strengths…"
有了這些力量…”
"With those strengths,
“有了這些力量
do whatever it takes to survive in this ugly and scary world."
就能繼續在這個 醜陋又恐怖的世界生存
"Whatever it takes to survive."
繼續生存”
It's so like you, Granny.
奶奶，這就是妳會說的話
Mr. Seo.
徐先生
Oh, you're early.
妳來早了
This is good. I like it. But isn't it too open?
這個不錯，我喜歡 但會不會不夠隱密？
Some people don't want to be seen when they're in sorrow.
有些人不喜歡 別人看見他們難過的樣子
That's true.
是沒錯
But it's a place where people can cry freely without thinking about others.
但這個地方是能讓人盡情哭泣 不用在意他人眼光的地方
I want them to just express their sorrow when they're here.
我希望他們能在那盡情表達哀痛
-Excuse me, sir. -Move!
-先生，不好意思 -走開
I'm really sorry. I sincerely apologize. It was my mistake.
我真的很抱歉 我誠心道歉，是我不對
Why did you let yourself make such a mistake?
你為什麼讓自己犯下這種錯誤？
Why the hell did you make a mistake when you were constructing that building?
你在建造那棟大樓時 怎麼能犯下這種錯誤？
Just express their sorrow? Would that be possible?
表達他們的哀痛？那有可能嗎？
Sorry?
你說什麼？
"Victims are filled with sadness."
“受害者悲痛不已”
"Poor people are nicer."
“窮困的人通常更善良”
"Disabled people are weak."
“肢障人士都是弱勢”
Those are preconceived notions.
那都是先入為主的觀念
Poor people can be greedy, and disabled people can be frauds.
窮困的人也會貪婪 肢障人士也可能是騙子
Victims can also be perpetrators.
受害者也可能是肇事者
Mr. Seo.
徐先生
The people who will visit the memorial park most often
會去紀念碑公園的人大多應該是
will probably be those who will live in that area.
住在附近的人
I understand where you're coming from.
我懂妳的出發點
But you're no longer just a victim.
但妳已經不是受害者了
Don't forget that you're an architect now.
別忘記妳現在是建築師了
I'm sorry. I said I'd leave it to you.
我很抱歉，我說過要全權交給妳決定
But I interfered too much.
但我干預太多
LAND SALE CONTRACT
（賣地契）
Wiring me the money today?
今天就能把錢給我嗎？
I will so you can't change your mind.
我會的，這樣你就不會改變心意
Jeez, I was always short of money no matter how hard I worked.
天啊，就算我工作再辛苦 錢老是不夠用
But you make easy gains.
但你隨便做都賺一堆錢
Hey! Do you know how much we're losing on this contract?
嘿，你知道這份合約 虧了我們多少錢嗎？
-Shall we do the math and see how much? -That's enough. Let's end it here.
-要不要算算看到底是多少錢？ -夠了，就此打住吧
You're not going to change your mind.
而且你的決定已經不能更改
Can I get back to work next week?
我下週能回去工作嗎？
I'll speak with the site manager first.
我要先跟工地主管說一下
Please tell him not to be so hard on me.
請跟他說別對我太兇
Gosh, that jerk really has nothing, including manners.
天啊，那個混小子也一點禮貌都沒有
Mr. Lee.
李先生
What? Is there anything else?
幹嘛？還有其他事情嗎？
Were you very close to the deceased?
你跟死者很熟嗎？
Why do you ask?
幹嘛問？
I'm curious to know why she gave the land to you.
我只是很好奇她為什麼要把地給你
You compete even with your family members, so it's not something you can understand.
妳連自家人都會爭權奪利 所以這種事不是妳能懂的
What are you going to do now?
你現在準備要怎麼做？
Does Ms. Ha know that you're coming back to the site?
河小姐知道你要回工地嗎？
I'm going to tell her.
我會跟她說的
What's with that face?
妳幹嘛那副表情？
You told me not to run away.
妳叫我不要逃避的
I'm just jealous of Ms. Ha.
我只是妒忌河小姐
I'm going to face it head on,
我決定要面對自己
so you can go in reverse or go straight.
妳可以選擇退卻，或是勇往直前
But try to work it out.
試著想辦法解決吧
He won't even budge.
他不會改變心意的
-What can I do by myself? -Then let him go.
-靠我自己能怎麼辦？ -那就讓他走
And if you have no courage to do so, just run away.
若妳沒勇氣這樣做，那就離開吧
I have nowhere to go.
我沒有地方可以去
Yes, you do.
有，妳有的
If people find out someone like you is loyal to one man,
若被人發現像妳這樣的人 居然死守著一個男人
they'll make fun of you.
他們會笑妳的
Wake up.
醒醒吧
Thank you for helping me modify the terms of the contract.
謝謝妳幫我修改合約上的條件
I figured it was worth it. That's why.
我只是覺得應該這樣做才對
Don't delude yourself.
不要想太多了
Oh, hey!
嘿
Gang-du!
康斗
-Drink this. -Thanks.
-給你喝 -謝謝
Chief was summoned to the head office. He couldn't even eat lunch.
主管被叫到總公司去 他連午餐都還沒吃
The news of your return made him so angry. It was good news for me though.
你能回來的消息讓他氣到不行 但對我來說可是好消息
-Was everything okay while I was gone? -Don't get me started on that.
-我不在的時候一切都還好嗎？ -說到這個就一肚子火
Mr. Seo kicked up a fuss, so we reinspected the ground.
徐先生之前好生氣 所以我們又檢查了一次地面
All we did was dispose of waste materials.
我們只是把廢物料都掩埋起來
"Where am I? Who am I?" I even suffered from an identity crisis.
“我在哪？我又是誰？” 我連自己是誰都搞不清楚了
That's why I've been waiting for you.
所以我一直在等你回來
-For me? -Yes.
-等我？ -對啊
-I was scared of being alone. -Why?
-我之前一個人都怕死了 -為什麼？
There's a strange rumor.
因為一個奇怪的傳言
-What rumor? -People keep seeing strange things.
-什麼傳言？ -有人一直看到奇怪的東西
You know this is a place where a big accident took place, right?
你知道這裡曾發生一場 很嚴重的意外吧？
There was a rumor that they just buried everything to wrap it up quickly.
傳言說他們只是 把所有東西都埋起來了事
They didn't even retrieve the bodies.
沒有把所有屍體挖掘出來
A chill runs down my spine whenever I'm on a night shift.
每次我值夜班都覺得全身發毛
What are you doing?
你在幹嘛？
I said, help me.
我叫你快來幫我
Hey! Wait!
嘿，等等
Get me out of here too!
也幫我脫困吧
There are people here!
這邊有人
What's wrong? Are you okay?
怎麼了？你還好嗎？
Yes, I am.
是的，我很好
Goodness.
我的老天啊
What's that? Hey, there!
那是幹嘛？嘿，小心啊
You need to be careful!
你們要小心啊
For goodness sake.
真是要命
Victims can also be perpetrators.
受害者也可能是肇事者
I understand where you're coming from.
我懂妳的出發點
But you're no longer just a victim.
但妳已經不是受害者了
Don't forget that you're an architect now.
別忘記妳現在是建築師了
Hey.
嘿
Hi.
嗨
-Hello? -Yes? What?
-你好？ -對，怎麼了？
What do you mean, what? You called me.
你幹嘛那樣問？是你打給我的耶
Oh, that's right. Did you eat?
沒錯，妳吃過了嗎？
I didn't feel like eating. What about you?
我不想吃，你呢？
Me neither. I just ate a little bit.
我也是，只吃了一點
Why did you eat just a little? You should eat well.
為什麼只吃一點？你應該要多吃點
Are you off work?
妳下班了嗎？
Yes. What about you?
下班了，那你呢？
What did you do today?
你今天做了什麼？
I took a walk.
我去散步了
Where did you go?
你去哪散步？
Just here and there.
隨處走走
While I was walking around…
當我在散步時
I realized that I was thinking about you.
我發現自己在想妳
I miss you.
我很想妳
Where are you now?
你在哪？
Oh, it's delicious.
真好吃
-You eat so prettily. -What?
-妳吃東西的樣子真好看 -你說什麼？
You must be busy being cute.
妳大概都忙著裝可愛吧
You said you had no appetite.
妳說妳不餓的
I had no appetite earlier.
我之前是不餓
But I became hungry when I saw you.
但我看到你之後就餓了
I want to eat mandu too. Do you want one?
我也想吃饅頭，你要不要一個？
Yes.
好
-One kimchi mandu, please. -Okay.
-請給我們一份泡菜饅頭 -好
-And five mandu to go.
-然後外帶五個饅頭
My mom and auntie love it.
我媽和我阿姨都很喜歡吃
-I'm glad. -What?
-我好開心 -幹嘛？
I'm glad I got to see you today.
我開心我今天能見到妳
Me too.
我也是
-Here you go. -Thank you.
-拿去吧 -謝謝
-Oh, it's hot! -Are you okay?
-好燙 -妳沒事吧？
No. Gosh, it's hot.
有事，天啊，好燙
It's so hot.
非常燙
But it's delicious.
但東西很好吃
It's nothing.
其實沒什麼
What?
你說什麼？
I mean, happiness.
我是說幸福
Granny! Are you watching us?
奶奶，妳在看著我們嗎？
SANHO PUBLIC BATH
（珊瑚公共澡堂）
Oh, dear. It's so cold.
天啊，好冷
OPEN
（營業中）
My goodness.
我的天啊
Auntie.
阿姨
Oh, you're home.
妳回來了啊
Nice. I was worried you'd already left.
太好了，我本來擔心妳已經走了
-Mandu. -Oh, I love it.
-饅頭 -我喜歡
Who's the guy that walked you home?
陪妳走回家的男人是誰？
Did you see him?
妳有看到他嗎？
Please don't tell Mom.
拜託千萬別跟媽說
Why not? I love seeing how lovey-dovey you young kids are.
為什麼？ 我好喜歡看在談情說愛的年輕人
Not now.
現在還不是時候
She won't approve.
她不會同意的
Not too many people in this world can make you smile like this.
世界上沒有太多人能讓妳笑成這樣
Your mom wouldn't be able to say anything if she saw your face now.
妳媽若能看到妳現在的樣子 她也不會多說什麼了
Goodness, look at you. You look so happy.
天啊，看看妳，妳看起來好開心
It's cold. Let's hurry in.
好冷，快點進去吧
27,300 won.
兩萬七千三百韓圓
I told you not to disturb me.
我說過別打擾我的
What is it?
怎麼了？
What are you doing with my girls during peak business hours?
現在生意這麼忙 你叫她們都在這裡幹嘛？
-I'll pay them. -You don't need all these girls.
-我會付她們的錢 -你不需要這麼多小姐
You're wasting your money, and we're taking a loss.
你在浪費錢，我們也在虧錢
Why should we do that?
我們為什麼要這樣？
Otherwise, you wouldn't even see me.
不然的話，妳根本不會見我
You left and didn't even answer my calls.
妳就這樣走了，又不接我的電話
If you feel sorry, just apologize. I'll accept it.
若你覺得自己不對 就道歉吧，我會接受的
I can't, so I'm doing this.
我辦不到，所以我才這樣做
I prefer throwing money at problems.
我比較喜歡用錢解決問題
That's the only way I know!
我只知道這種方法
You're disgusted with me, right?
妳很厭惡我，對吧？
I know.
我知道
Not many people like me.
沒有很多人喜歡我
-You know? -Yes.
-你真的知道嗎？ -知道
People always grovel to me, but they talk behind my back.
大家都喜歡拍我馬屁 但總是在我背後講我壞話
Did you think I didn't know?
妳以為我不知道嗎？
It's a relief if you do.
你既然知道就太好了
But don't worry about it.
但別擔心了
No matter what they do, they're just your subordinates.
不管他們怎麼做都只是你的下屬
That's why they curse you.
所以他們才會罵你
I know that too.
這一點我也知道
I signed the contract with Lee Gang-du.
我跟李康斗簽約了
He was supposed to express his gratitude to me, but he didn't!
他本來該答謝我的大恩大德 但他根本不在乎
Good. You should smile. You look pretty when you smile.
很好，妳是該笑，妳笑的時候很美
Why? Do I look like your first love when I smile?
為什麼？我笑起來就像你的初戀嗎？
You do.
是沒錯
But that's not why I like you.
但那不是我喜歡妳的原因
That wench was bad.
那個女人很爛
At least you don't talk crap about love.
至少妳不會把愛視為糞土
You're cool about love. And that's what I like about you.
妳懂愛，所以我才喜歡妳
You'll come with me to Eulsukdo Island, right?
妳會跟我去乙淑島，對吧？
-What are you doing, Gang-du? -Hey.
-康斗，你在幹嘛？ -嘿
The man from room 201 picked this up.
住在201號房的人拿得動這個
I'm exhausted from hanging it up.
我光掛上去就累死了
-Doesn't it look cool? -Yes.
-看起來是不是很酷？ -是啊
It clears your head too.
也能理清思緒
I think it's a good one.
這個是還不錯
Ms. Kim.
金小姐
-Are you okay, Ms. Kim? -No.
-金小姐，妳還好嗎？ -不好
I didn't sleep for several days.
我已經好幾天沒睡了
I worked really hard to meet the deadline.
為趕上交期，我很努力工作
But did I do all that only to be criticized like this?
但我這麼辛苦 卻只能得到這些批評嗎？
I'm fed up with it.
我已經受夠了
Fine.
好吧
I'll quit everything. That won't hurt me.
我不幹了，反正我也無所謂
I don't have any pleasure in my life.
我的人生一點樂趣都沒有
What will you do if you quit?
若真的放棄了，妳要做什麼？
Whatever you do, you can't avoid criticism.
不管妳做什麼都會有人批評的
Just be grateful that you can do what you like for a living.
妳應該要感謝自己能做 喜歡的工作維持生計
Hey, have you forgotten that you used to post hate comments?
嘿，你忘記你之前 也寫過那樣的留言嗎？
You only complained despite the chances you had, so I was mad.
那是因為儘管妳有機會 卻只會抱怨，所以我才生氣
But I shouldn't have made personal attacks. I'm sorry.
但我不該做人身攻擊
Forget it.
算了
Why do I keep on doing this work?
為什麼我老畫這個漫畫？
"If you just run away, you can never get to heaven.
“若逃跑，就永遠到不了天堂
All you'll see is…"
只能隨處見到…”
"Battlegrounds."
“戰場”
Don't think about anything. Just get some rest.
什麼都別想了，休息一下吧
I'll assist you starting tomorrow.
我明天會來幫妳
I must be out of my mind!
我一定是瘋了
MEMORIAL PARK SITE CHANGE
（紀念碑地點更動）
FUTURE PLANS
（未來計畫）
Mr. Jung gladly approved this?
鄭先生欣然同意了嗎？
Not gladly.
並不是很高興
But anyway, he did.
但總之他同意了
-The memorial park design is… -I know Mun-su is working on it.
-紀念碑公園的設計… -我知道文秀在負責這個案子
I'll help her from the site when I get back.
我回來後就可以幫她
Didn't Ms. Jung tell you?
鄭小姐沒跟你說嗎？
It's kind of sudden. What happened?
這件事很突然，發生什麼事情了嗎？
Luckily, a person like me got a chance too.
幸運的是
So I seized it.
所以我抓住了機會
You know I have feelings for Mun-su.
你知道我喜歡文秀
Your private life is not my concern.
你的私人生活跟我無關
-Why are you coming back-- -Because of Mun-su.
-你為什麼回來… -因為文秀
I gave up on her because I didn't think I could become a good person like you.
我放棄她
But if I make an effort,
但若我願意努力
I think I can become a good person to at least one person.
我想我至少能讓一個人覺得我很棒
I'm going to give it a try.
我要試試看
Why are you here?
你來這裡幹嘛？
I'm here to work. Why else would I be here?
我是因為公事而來，不然我來幹嘛？
Here?
這裡？
-You're moving it here? -Yes.
-你要移到這裡？ -對
It's the center.
是中間的位置
Exactly.
沒錯
It stands out. And people can see it as they walk by.
這樣會很顯眼，走過時都會看到
It's nice.
很不錯
Nothing is going to change. You just go ahead with your plan.
其他都不變，妳可以照妳的計畫進行
What is this?
這是什麼？
Come to think of it, my dad used to write in this notebook when he came home.
我之前想到我爸以前回家時 都會在這本記事簿上寫東西
I think you'd understand what he had written.
我想妳看得懂他在寫什麼
How the shopping mall was built
關於購物商場是如何建造的
and what problems it had.
和其中有什麼問題
-Are you leaving? -Yes. I have something to do.
-你要走了嗎？ -對，我還有事情要做
Oh, right.
對了，我們晚點一定至少要見個面
Why?
為什麼？
I'm planning to look super cool today.
我計畫今天要好好打扮一下
-Would you like to see more suits? -Yes.
-還想看更多西裝嗎？ -好
Just a moment, please.
請先等一下
-Gang-du. Let's leave. -Why?
-康斗，我們走吧 -為什麼？
Look at this place. It looks very expensive.
看看這個地方
-We don't have money. -We do.
-我們又沒錢 -我們有
We do?
我們有嗎？
Yes. Go pick out a pair of shoes too.
對啊，去選一雙鞋子吧
Shoes? Hurray!
鞋子？太棒了
What?
搞什麼？
Hey. What on earth…
嘿，到底是在…
DAY LOAN UP TO 50 MILLION WON
（每日借款高達五千萬韓圓）
Shit.
天啊
Is it real?
這是真鈔嗎？
-Yes. -My god.
-是的 -天啊
Gang-du.
康斗
See you again.
再見了
Why would I see you again? I won't.
我為什麼會再看到你？ 我們不會見面了
Let's go.
走吧
Come again.
再來喔
Did you see them grovel to me?
你有看到他們畢恭畢敬的樣子嗎？
They harassed me for years.
他們騷擾我好多年了
-Did you see? -Yes.
-你有看到嗎？ -有
Gosh! Money is good!
天啊，有錢真好
It's so good!
感覺超好的
Gang-du. I'm hungry.
康斗，我餓了
What are we going to eat?
我們要吃什麼？
B-11?
B-11？
B-11 ZONE
（B-11區）
The shopping mall blueprint? Why do you need it?
購物商場的藍圖？妳要那個幹嘛？
It's been over ten years, so Mr. Seo must have it.
已經超過十年了，徐先生那邊一定有
Go ask him.
去找他要吧
Can you get it for me?
你能幫我去跟他要嗎？
Gang-du. Judging from the way things have been going, this isn't right.
康斗，端看事情的走向 這樣不太對吧
What's best in the winter?
冬天什麼東西最棒？
-Fish cakes. -Correct.
-魚板 -沒錯
-It's good, right? -Yes, it is.
-很好吃，對吧？ -是沒錯
Gang-du. We have a lot of money now. Let's just buy this store.
康斗，我們現在是有錢人了 就把這間店買下來吧
Then we can eat fish cakes all winter long.
這樣就可以吃一整個冬天的魚板
It's not my money.
那不是我的錢
I need to work hard until the day I die to repay Granny.
我得努力工作到死，才能回報奶奶
-Gang-du, I think God exists. -What?
-康斗，我覺得神真的存在 -你說什麼？
I think he sent Granny to you because he felt sorry for you.
我認為奶奶是祂派來的 因為祂覺得你很可憐
He must've felt really sorry.
祂一定覺得很抱歉
I'll eat something spicy too.
我還要吃辣的東西
Tteokbokki, please.
請給我辣炒年糕
-He sent you to me too. -What?
-祂也把你派來我身邊 -你說什麼？
Nothing. Enjoy.
沒什麼，吃吧
Give me one too.
也給我一個
Welcome.
歡迎光臨
He isn't back yet. Wait for him in his room.
他還沒回來，去他房間等他吧
-Not yet? -I don't know.
-還沒？ -我也不知道
The two of them went out and haven't called all day.
他們兩個一起出去了 一整天了都沒打電話回來
I'll call them now.
我現在打給他們
-Go up. -Okay.
-上去吧 -好
It smells good. Thank you.
聞起來真香，謝謝
Hey. Where are you guys?
嘿，你們在哪啊？
It's way past dinnertime. Why aren't you coming home?
已經過晚餐時間了 為什麼還不回家？
Could you bring one of his pills to me?
請妳把他在吃的藥拿一顆給我好嗎？
Look at these little pills. When it goes into your body,
看看這些藥丸，吞下去後
your brain can't feel any pain.
妳就不會覺得痛了
Imagine how toxic it must be to fool your body like that.
想像一下它有多毒，能騙過妳的身體
I told you I was planning to look cool today.
我說過我計畫今天要好好打扮一下
Why are you all dressed up? Is it a special day?
你幹嘛穿得這麼正式？ 今天很特別嗎？
-Yes. -What special day is it?
-當然 -是什麼特別的日子？
The day I was reborn as a contributing member of society.
今天我重新誕生為一個很特別的人
What?
你說什麼？
Won't you congratulate me?
不恭喜我嗎？
How?
怎麼恭喜？
Mun-su! Look at me! Gang-du bought me a suit…
文秀看看我，康斗幫我買了一套…
Go ahead. Finish what you were doing.
請繼續，完成你們剛在做的事情
I'm a good-for-nothing.
我發現自己真的很沒用
All I know is martial arts. It's all useless.
一直只知道練功，一點用都沒有
Hi, Wan-jin.
婉珍
Goodness.
我的天啊
What's going on?
怎麼了？
You told me to hurry home.
妳叫我趕快回家的
Did I?
我有嗎？
She said she ran away.
她說她逃走了
-What? -Ma'am.
-什麼？ -阿姨
From what I heard, it's true. She ran away from a man.
就我聽到的來說是真的 她在躲一個男人
A man?
一個男人？
You finish this. I'm going upstairs.
給妳做完吧，我要上樓了
You're young, single, and interested in him.
妳年輕又是單身，而且又喜歡他
Why would you run away?
為什麼還要躲他？
That's my house. I didn't run away.
那是我家，我沒有躲他
If you like him, date him. Once you do it, it won't be a big deal.
若妳喜歡他，就約他出去吧
-I'll sleep here tonight. -Okay.
-我今晚會睡在這裡 -好
What is it?
到底怎麼了？
You're always with him. Of course he's on your mind.
妳老跟他在一起 當然滿腦子都在想他
It's not like that.
不是那樣的
I can only see his good sides, and it's driving me insane.
我只看到他好的一面，那讓我很心煩
He's reliable for his age.
以他這個年紀來說他是挺可靠
And he's more diligent than I thought.
而他也比我想得要更努力
It seems like he's lived a tough life, but he didn't go astray.
感覺起來他的生活不易 但他也沒走偏
That shouldn't drive you insane. You should be happy.
那不該讓妳心煩才對，妳應該開心
-Hey. You should stop me. -Why?
-嘿，妳該打住我的想法 -為什麼？
If I go crazy and come on to him, that's considered sexual harassment.
若我一下失控撲向他 那可算是性騷擾
He seems to be interested in you too.
他感覺起來也喜歡妳
He used to post hate comments about you but then suddenly came to assist you.
他以前留那些惡評給妳 現在突然來幫妳
Think about how he treats you. The answer is obvious.
想想他對妳的態度吧，答案可想而知
Forget it. No, it can't happen. Stop.
算了，不，這種事情不會發生，停止
You made it even worse.
妳讓事情更糟了
What about you? You got to see Gang-du today, right?
那妳呢？妳今天見到康斗了，對吧？
Come on. Hey, aren't you going to tell me?
快說，妳不會連我都想瞞吧？
What?
妳在講什麼？
Tell me.
快跟我說
-There's nothing to tell you. -Tell me.
-沒什麼好說的 -告訴我
-What? -Aren't you going to tell me? Hey.
-什麼啦？ -妳不跟我說嗎？嘿
I won't stop until you tell me.
妳不說我就繼續潑妳
RED CLAY SAUNA FOR WOMEN
（為女性設計的紅泥三溫暖）
Hey.
嘿
-I put the clothes… -Tell me.
-我把衣服… -告訴我
-Tell you what? -What happened? Hey.
-跟妳說什麼啊？ -到底發生了什麼事？嘿
-Tell me. -Nothing happened.
-告訴我 -根本沒發生任何事
Come on. Tell me.
少來，跟我說
Hey, aren't you going to tell me?
嘿，妳不跟我說嗎？
I'm going to do this until you tell me.
妳不跟我說我就繼續潑水
Just tell me.
跟我說吧
Nothing happened.
根本沒發生任何事情
I think something happened between you two.
我認為你們之間一定有發生什麼事情
-How's your mother? -She drank all night.
-妳媽媽還好嗎？ -她喝了一夜的酒
She can't even get up today.
她今天根本起不來
Here.
拿去
Wan-jin, what's the color of the pill you just took?
婉珍，妳剛吃的藥是什麼顏色？
What? Maybe white. Why do you ask?
什麼？也許是白色吧，幹嘛問？
The pills Gang-du takes are blue.
康斗吃的藥是藍色的
Is that so important?
那很重要嗎？
No.
也不是
I hope it isn't.
我希望是沒什麼
Thank you. I was worried he'd pretend to be fine if I asked for it.
謝謝，我擔心若我問他 他也不會老實跟我說他的情況
Please let me know if it's something bad for him.
若有東西對他不好，請讓我知道
Okay. Bye, then.
好，再見了
Wait.
等等
What you told me the other day.
妳之前跟我說的事情
About the accident.
關於意外
He spent days with a dead body.
他跟一具屍體困在一起好幾天
It'll only torment him to remember that.
讓他想到那一點只是在折磨他
You said he didn't tell you.
妳說他沒有跟妳說過
Ask him yourself if you want to know more.
若妳想知道更多答案就去問他吧
Even though we're family, I don't think I should talk about it.
儘管我們是家人 但我認為妳該去問他
Mr. Moon Byeong-ho's body wasn't retrieved.
文承浩先生的屍體從沒有被找到
He had a wife and a son.
他有一個太太和一個兒子
Huh?
嗯？
It's here.
就是這裡
I must be materialistic.
我大概把物質看得太重了
The fact that she lives in this nice house makes me feel a bit relieved.
看到她住在這麼漂亮的房子
Just a minute.
等一下
Tae-ho, go into your room.
太浩，請先回自己的房間
Hurry.
快點
He thinks my second husband is his real dad.
他認為我第二個丈夫是他的親生父親
Oh, I see. I got it.
我懂了
-Please read this first-- -No.
-請先讀這個… -不了
I don't think it's something you need my consent for.
我不認為妳有任何東西 會需要我的同意
Does he have any other family?
他還有其他家人嗎？
His father passed away a few years ago.
他爸爸幾年前過世了
And I heard his older brother emigrated.
我聽說他的哥哥移民了
I lost contact with them long ago.
我很久以前就沒跟他們聯絡了
Do you think I'm bad?
妳認為我很差勁嗎？
No. Thank you for meeting with us like this.
不會，謝謝妳肯見我們
I heard the place is under construction.
我聽說那個地方正在大興土木
Yes.
是的
It'll be gone for real then.
那就真的找不到了
We couldn't even find a bone from his body.
我們根本找不到一塊 屬於他屍體的骨頭
So now,
現在
it feels like he's away on a long journey.
感覺起來好像他只是去遠行
I just can't find an answer, so I'm just going to forget about it.
我得不到答案，所以我決定忘掉一切
I won't suffer if there's nothing to remember.
若沒有東西要記得，就不會痛苦
We're sorry.
我們深感遺憾
We'll take care of this.
這個東西我們會處理
VICTIM INFORMATION MOON BYEONG-HO
（受害者資料文承浩）
DATE OF BIRTH: APRIL 21, 1973
（文承浩，1973年4月21日出生）
This is what he looked like.
那是他當時的樣子
I only wanted to forget the bad things.
我只想忘記不好的事情
But now, I don't remember the good times either.
但現在我連愉快的時光也記不起來了
-What? -Don't you feel the same way?
-怎麼了？ -你沒同感嗎？
Don't you want to forget it all?
你不想忘記一切嗎？
Isn't this stressful for you?
這樣做沒給你很大的壓力嗎？
What about you? Isn't it hard for you?
講得好像這和妳沒有關係 對妳來說不痛苦嗎？
I don't know…
我不知道
if I can do this well or what is right.
我能不能把這個案子做好 或是做得完善
There's no right answer.
這種事沒有標準答案
We just need to do what we can and do our best.
我們只能盡力做到最好
Let's go.
我們走吧
You need to get back.
妳得回去了
It's cold. Let's take a taxi.
好冷，我們搭計程車吧
It's rush hour.
現在是尖峰時刻
The bus will take me directly to the office.
公車會直接帶我回公司
Why did you wear something so thin if you were going to take the bus?
如果知道要搭公車 妳為什麼穿這麼單薄？
I thought it was inappropriate to wear a sweater as a visitor.
我覺得去拜訪別人穿套頭衫很不禮貌
For goodness sake.
我的老天啊
-No, don't take it off. -Why not?
-不要，別脫下來 -為什麼不要？
You'll be cold too then.
你也會很冷
I'd rather shiver in the cold than see you shiver in the cold.
我寧願自己冷得發抖 也不想看到你冷得發抖
I mean it.
我是說真的
All right. I won't take it off.
好，我不會脫的
Instead…
不然…
Until the bus comes, let's stay like this.
公車來之前我們就抱在一起吧
What? You're heavy.
這是怎樣？你好重
Endure it.
忍耐吧
-Is it because you run a bathhouse? -What?
-是因為妳家開澡堂嗎？ -什麼？
You smell good.
妳聞起來很香
NOODLES AND GIMBAP
（麵食和海苔飯捲）
Jeez, my personal trainer told me not to eat flour-based foods.
天啊，我的健身教練叫我不要吃麵食
You look fine, Mr. Jung.
鄭先生，你身材看起來很好
I'm in good shape because I work out regularly.
我身材好，是因為我常運動
If I get a pot-belly, my wife will…
若我有鮪魚肚，我太太會…
What's wrong? We're not dating.
怎麼了？我們又不是在約會
Hey, we eat and drink coffee together.
嘿，我們一起吃東西又喝咖啡
What we're doing now is kind of like dating.
我們現在這樣就像在約會
Do you own any land around here?
妳在這裡有任何土地嗎？
Of course not. And I don't like real estate.
當然沒有，我不喜歡房地產
I prefer movable assets. Then I can leave at any time.
我比較喜歡能移動的資產 這樣我要走就可以走
You can't leave.
妳不能走
If you want to make money, stay here.
若妳想賺錢就留下來
I'll redevelop this area next year.
我明年會開發這個地區
I haven't been able to do it for the past ten years.
我過去十年都沒辦法做到
If I don't do it next year, the permits will expire…
若我明年不開發 我的許可證就會過期…
Forget it. Just buy some land before that.
算了，在那之前買些地吧
Should I buy you some?
要不要我幫妳買？
I feel a deep sense of responsibility for the shopping mall collapse.
購物商場倒塌 我深深感覺自己要負責
I'll bow my head in apology.
我要鞠躬表達深切歉意
We worked really hard on it to make up for lost time.
我們很努力工作要彌補失去的時間
All this area will be… Oh, gosh!
整個地區都會…天啊
-What do you think you're doing? -Get out.
-你到底在幹什麼？ -滾出去
-Why are you doing this, sir? -I said, get out!
-先生，你幹嘛這樣？ -我說滾出去
This man is crazy!
這個人瘋了
Let's go. I'll ask him why he did this later.
走吧，我等一下會問他原因
Jeez.
天啊
The shopping mall blueprint.
購物商場的藍圖
There isn't much to look at.
其實沒什麼好看的
My team reviewed it once before but didn't find any problems.
我的組員之前就看過一次 但什麼問題都沒發現
-Then why did he die? -Sorry?
-那他為什麼會死？ -妳說什麼？
The architect. I heard he committed suicide.
建築師，我聽說他自殺了
-Really? -Did he?
-真的嗎？ -有嗎？
He wouldn't have died if he had been innocent.
若他是無辜的，就不會想死
I wouldn't. It wouldn't be fair.
我就不會，感覺被誤解了
-Is that so? -It's strange.
-是嗎？ -很奇怪
How could he die irresponsibly like that after giving a word of apology?
他為什麼在道歉之後 就這樣不負責任地了結自己的生命？
Are you okay, Mun-su?
文秀，妳還好嗎？
I'll get you water.
我幫妳拿點水吧
Mr. Seo.
徐先生
Go home. You don't look well.
回家吧，妳看起來不太好
No.
不用
How could he die irresponsibly like that after throwing out an apology?
他為什麼在道歉之後 就這樣不負責任地了結自己的生命？
You killed all those people. You think sorry is going to cut it?
你殺了那些人 你覺得道歉就能解決問題嗎？
Is this such an easy problem to you?
這種事對你來說這麼無足輕重嗎？
Darn it.
該死
Look at your face. My goodness.
看看你的臉，天啊
-What brings you here? -I didn't volunteer to come.
-妳來這裡幹嘛？ -我可不想來
I came instead of Mun-su.
我是代替文秀來的
Instead of Mun-su?
代替文秀？
She called in sick today.
她今天打來請病假
-She's sick? -You didn't know?
-她生病了？ -你不知道嗎？
Oh, that must've been because you were busy flirting with Ms. Jung.
大概是因為 你忙著在跟鄭小姐打情罵俏吧
What are you saying?
妳在講什麼？
I hate the kind of guy who hits on every girl he sees.
我最討厭那種見一個愛一個的男人
Do you have an extra pair of work shoes? I don't want to get my pants dirty.
你有多的工作鞋嗎？ 我不想把我的褲子弄髒
About Mun-su. What seems to be the problem?
關於文秀，她是生什麼病？
Gosh, it's chilly. Come and take a sauna.
天啊，好冷，去洗三溫暖吧
-I'm okay. -No, you're not.
-我很好 -才怪，妳根本不好
Sweating is the best remedy for a cold.
流汗對感冒最有用
Take a hot bath and go up to get some rest.
先去洗一個熱水澡，然後上去休息吧
Come on. Hurry up and go.
趕快，快點上去吧
-Hey. -I heard you're sick.
-嘿 -我聽說妳生病了
I'm fine now.
我現在沒事了
You don't sound fine at all.
妳聽起來完全不像沒事
I'm getting better.
我有比較好了
Gosh, your clothes were too thin yesterday.
天啊，妳昨天穿得太單薄了
Did you eat something?
妳有吃東西嗎？
I have a sore throat, so I can't eat anything.
我喉嚨痛，所以沒辦法吃
What should I feed you? Is there anything you want to eat?
我該買什麼給妳吃？ 妳有想吃的東西嗎？
Ice cream.
冰淇淋
I'll eat ice cream.
我會吃冰淇淋
Ice cream? Do you have some at home?
冰淇淋？妳家裡有嗎？
I don't know.
我不知道
What time is it now?
現在幾點了？
You're up.
妳起來了
-Come on out. Eat and sleep. -Okay.
-快出來吃東西，然後睡覺 -好
I'll call you later.
我晚點打給你
Why are you not eating?
妳為什麼不吃？
For goodness sake.
我的老天
Mix it with the soup and eat a few mouthfuls.
跟湯拌在一起，然後吃個幾口
I have a sore throat. I can't eat anymore.
我喉嚨痛，我吃不下去了
You need to eat to take medicine!
妳要吃東西才能吃藥
GANG-DU
（康斗）
Why isn't she answering?
她為什麼不接電話？
Mom.
媽
Oh. Hello. Nice to meet you.
妳好，很開心認識妳
GANG-DU FOUR MISSED CALLS
（康斗，四通未接來電）
What are you doing?
你在幹嘛？
Goodness.
我的天啊
Are you crazy?
你瘋了嗎？
Ice cream--
-冰淇淋… -噓
-What's going on? -You wanted ice cream.
-發生什麼事了？ -妳說妳想吃冰淇淋
I thought you were asleep, so I was going to hang it on the window.
我想說妳大概在睡覺 所以本來想掛在窗戶上
Goodness.
天啊
-Mun-su. -What do we do?
-文秀 -我們該怎麼辦？
Are you sleeping, Mun-su?
文秀，妳睡了嗎？
Hey, it's dangerous.
太危險了
Go under this. Hurry.
快躲到下面，快點
Lie down.
躺下來
I dozed off.
我剛睡著了
Why did you lock the door?
妳幹嘛把門鎖上？
I didn't know it was locked.
我不知道鎖上了
Goodness. I was worried.
天啊，害我擔心
What's wrong with your face? Are you getting a fever again?
妳的臉怎麼了？是不是又發燒了？
It's just hot in here because of the heater.
是因為暖氣，所以房裡很熱
-What's up? -Drink this before going to sleep.
-怎麼了？ -睡覺前把這個喝了
I boiled ginger and dates.
我煮了紅棗薑湯
It's hot.
好燙
Goodness, you need to cool it down.
天啊，妳要等涼一點才能喝
Put it next to you and drink it when you're thirsty.
放在床旁邊，口渴就可以喝了
Goodness.
天啊
Aren't you leaving?
妳還不出去嗎？
After I see you lie down. Go. I'll turn off the light for you.
我要看到妳躺下來 快點，我會幫妳關燈
Okay.
好
Lie down.
躺下來啊
Sleep tight.
好好睡
It's safe now. Come out.
你安全了，出來吧
Come out.
快出來
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
What if you catch a cold from me?
萬一你被我傳染感冒怎麼辦？
You might catch a cold.
你很可能會感冒
That's good.
那也好
I'll take all your cold viruses.
我會把妳的感冒病毒都帶走
What do we do?
我們現在該怎麼辦？
It's obvious. I'll go out the way I came in.
想也知道，我要從進來的地方出去
-What? -I'll get going.
-什麼？ -我要走了
Hey.
嘿
You scared me.
你嚇死我了
I'll go for real.
我這次是真的要走了
-Are you okay? -Yes.
-你沒事吧？ -沒事
Go back in.
快進去吧
SANHO PUBLIC BATH
（珊瑚公共澡堂）
You were dying yesterday.
妳昨天都快死了
I guess I ate and slept well. I'm full of energy.
我想是因為吃好睡好吧 我感覺精力充沛
Goodness. It's good to be young.
真是，年輕真好
-I'm off to work. -Bye.
-我要去上班了 -再見
Hey. Wear a scarf, or you'll get sick again.
戴個圍巾，不然妳又會生病了
I'll be fine. Bye.
我不會有事的，再見
For goodness sake.
我的天啊
I don't like it when she's like that.
她這麼倔強真討人厭
THE COLLAPSED SHOPPING MALL
（倒塌的購物商場 將會重生為生命的搖籃）
A pillar came out during excavation. I feel uneasy about it.
挖掘時挖到一根柱子 讓我覺得怪怪的
To move it, we need to demolish it first.
若要移走它，就需要先打碎
Should we dig in the spot?
我們要在那個地點開挖嗎？
No. There's no need to go through the hassle.
不，不需要這麼麻煩
Handle it as waste.
把它當廢料處理吧
As waste?
當廢料？
Yes.
對
BUS STOP: SPACE S MALL
（公車站：S空間商場）
MEDICAL INNOVATION CITY, BIOTOWN
（創新醫療城市，綠建築小鎮）
SPECIAL THANKS TO LEE JI-HYEON
（特別鳴謝李芝賢）
How did you know Mun-su likes the type of guy who enjoys carrots?
你怎麼知道 文秀喜歡愛吃胡蘿蔔的人？
Do I?
我有嗎？
But isn't it nice?
但這樣很好啊
He can eat neither chicken feet nor soju.
他不吃雞腳，也不喝燒酒
You sure he's not picky?
妳確定他不挑嗎？
Love makes people become biased like that.
愛情會讓人盲目
I'm really fine. I don't need anything.
我真的沒關係，我什麼都不需要
Yes, you're fine.
對，妳是都不需要
Even though I'm slow-witted, I won't ask you to pick out your own gift.
雖然我不是很聰明 但我也不會讓妳挑自己的禮物
-When did you buy this? -When you weren't looking.
-你什麼時候買的？ -趁妳不注意的時候
I'm jealous of you. You work and date at the same time.
我真妒忌妳，妳能邊工作邊約會
You startled me.
你嚇到我了
I fooled you. When did you come?
我騙到妳了，妳什麼時候來的？
A while ago.
到一會了
You guys meet, eat fish cakes, take a walk,
你們會見面，一起吃魚板，又去散步
and play on the swings,
又去盪鞦韆
and you walk her home.
你又陪她走回家
A suite is as cheap as a motel room.
一間套房跟一間車旅一樣便宜
You can watch movies and satisfy your fleshly desires too.
可以看電影，還可以滿足身體需要
There are places like that? It's fascinating.
真的有那種地方嗎？真有趣
Stay here.
待在這裡
If that hadn't happened, everything would've been fine.
若那件事沒有發生，那一切都會沒事
So we must work hard to be happier…
所以我們一定要努力工作才能比…
Gang-du!
康斗
…than anyone else.
…其他人都還要快樂
Subtitle translation by: Jungyun Ahn
字幕翻譯：Lin